Guide to the Benjamin Severance Winchester Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Benjamin Severance Winchester Papers
1903-1938
RG 252
Yale University Divinity School Library
8
(17 boxes)
The collection chronicles the life and work of Benjamin Severance Winchester, who began serving as a Congregationalist minister and religious educator in 1897 and was active into the 1930s. During his career Winchester lived and worked in Washington, Illinois, Massachusetts, New York, and Connecticut. Most of the collection details religious education curriculum in various fields, including sexual education, race relations education, Prohibition education, and peace education. Correspondence, curriculum, meeting minutes, and reports stem from Winchester's work with multiple organizations, including the Federal Council of Churches of Christ in America and the International Council of Religious Education.
Winchester, Benjamin S. (Benjamin Severance), 1868-1955
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Cris Carvalho, 2012
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Chronology
1868 February 26 Born in Bridport, Vermont to Catharine Mary Severance Winchester and Warren Weaver Winchester, a Congregationalist minister.
1889 Graduated from Williams College, Williamstown, Massachusetts
1889-1892 Professor of Chemistry and Natural Sciences at Whitman College, Walla Walla, Washington
1895 Received Bachelor of Divinity degree from Chicago Theological Seminary
1895-1897 Studied theology on fellowship at the University of Halle in Germany
1897 Married Pearl (Rose) Adair Gunn of Seattle, WA
1897 Ordained as a Congregationalist minister
1897-1900 Served as a minister, Snohomish, Washington
1900-1901 Served as a minister, Portland, Oregon
1901-1903 Served as a minister in the New England Church, Chicago, Illinois
1904-1909 Served as minister in Winnetka, Illinois
1910 Received honorary degree of Doctor of Divinity from Chicago Theological Seminary
1910-1916 Editor and Educational Secretary of the Congregational Sunday School Publishing Society (The Pilgrim Press) of Boston, MA
1915-1918 Yale Divinity School Professor
1918-1926 Pastor at Greenfield Hill Congregational Church, Fairfield, Connecticut
1918-1931 Education Secretary of the Federal Council of Churches of Christ in America, Christian Education chairman
1929-1931 President of the Hymn Society of America
1931-1938 Pastor at the Gilbert Memorial Church (Congregationalist), Georgetown, Connecticut
1932-1936 Worked heavily with the International Council of Religious Education (especially Adult Education and Education Leadership)
1935 Officer on the Committee of African Welfare of the Commission on Race Relations and Committee on International Justice and Goodwill of the Federal Council of Churches
1936-1938 Worked closely with the Hymn Society of America
1937 Board member of the John Milton Foundation
1938 Moves with Mrs. Winchester to Newtown, CT
1938-1955 Active in the Newtown Congregational Church, served as chairman of the Religious Education Committee
1955 April 29 Died in Danbury, Connecticut, at the age of 87. Survived by wife, Pearl Adair Gunn Winchester, daughters Miss Margaret Winchester, Mrs. E.T. Wakeman, Mrs. R.G. Inman, and Miss Alice Winchester.
Scope and Contents
This collection provides valuable insight into the work of an early twentieth-century religious educator, Reverend Benjamin Severance Winchester. Winchester began serving in religious education and as a Congregationalist minister in 1897. He lived and worked in Washington, Illinois, Massachusetts, New York, and Connecticut. During his career, Winchester taught religious education at multiple schools and churches, including the Yale Divinity School. He worked most extensively with the Federal Council of Churches of Christ in America and the International Council of Religious Education. The collection contains valuable information on American social and religious attitudes in the 1910s, 1920s, and 1930s.
Series I, Correspondence, contains two types of letters. Personal Correspondence contains letters to and from Winchester's family, friends, and former congregants. Professional Correspondence shows the diversity of Winchester's activities and interests. Winchester corresponded with the Congregational Sunday School Publishing Society (The Pilgrim's Press), various religious organizations, and provided professional advice. Some letters also focus on Winchester's published writings.
Series II contains Writings by Winchester. These include pamphlets, speeches, book-length works, and published articles. Winchester published several books, but drafts here include "The Teaching Church" and "Curricula of Christian Education." Articles in this series focus on hymns, movies, patriotism, adult education, and the debate over religious education in public schools.
Most valuable to the Winchester collection is Series III, Subject files. Included are correspondence, meeting minutes, committee reports, and pamphlets from a wide variety of religious and social organizations. Most of the Series details religious education in various fields, including sexual education, race relations education, Prohibition education, and peace education. Of particular interest are surveys completed by young people, 12 to 18 years old. The most numerous surveys come from Northeastern and Midwestern states and focus on race relations, sexual attitudes, and Prohibition opinions. Included as well are Typical and Life Situations, which were created to teach young people proper morals in real life situations. The Series also contains curriculum for Marriage and Home-life education and Family and Parent religious education.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence
II. Writings
III. Subject Files
Religious education; Winchester, Benjamin S. (Benjamin Severance), 1868-1955
- Correspondence, 1907-1938; Series I
  - Personal correspondence, 1907-1935
    - Including regarding summer plans, daughter's college bills, moving to New Haven, 1907, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Including to/from relatives, regarding daughter's college bills, 1916 Jan-Aug (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Including to/from relatives, to/from former congregants, regarding Williams class reunion, 1916 Sep-1918 Feb (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Information to/from friends, to/from family, Pi Gamma Mu membership, insurance/railroad accident information, 1925 Mar-1933 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Including regarding son's college expenses, to/from relatives, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Professional correspondence
    - Including to/from other religious educators, the Congregational Sunday School & Publishing Society (The Pilgrim Press), 1912 March, 1914 Aug, 1915 Jan-March (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Including to/from other religious educators, the Congregational Sunday School & Publishing Society (The Pilgrim Press), Yale Divinity School appointment, 1915 April-June (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Including to/from Congregational Sunday School & Publishing Society (The Pilgrim Press), regarding Yale Divinity School appointment, Eagles Mere religious summer school, 1915 July-Aug (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Including to/from Congregational Sunday School & Publishing Society (The Pilgrim Press), regarding Yale Divinity School appointment, 1915 Sept-Oct (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Including to/from Congregational Sunday School & Publishing Society, the International Sunday School Association, regarding professional advice from Winchester, 1915 Nov-Dec (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Including to/from Congregational Sunday School & Publishing Society, the International Sunday School Association, regarding professional advice from Winchester, College voluntary study courses, various meetings with religious organizations, 1916 Jan-Feb (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Including to/from Congregational Sunday School & Publishing Society, regarding professional advice from Winchester, College volunatry study courses, various meetings with religious organizations, missionary education, hymn books, 1916 Feb-Apr (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Including to/from Congregational Sunday School & Publishing Society, regarding professional advice from Winchester, missionary education, hymn books, 1916 Apr-May (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Including to/from Congregational Sunday School & Publishing Society, regarding professional advice from Winchester, missionary education, hymn books, 1916 May-June (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Including regarding professional advice and referrals from Winchester, Yale Divinity School, speaking requests to Winchester from various religious organizations and congregations, 1916 July-Sept (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Including regarding professional advice and referrals from Winchester, speaking requests to Winchester from various religious organizations and congregations, 1916 Sept-Dec (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Including speaking requests to Winchester from various religious organizations and congregations, regarding Winchester's appointment to Chairman of Education with the Federal Council of the Churches of Christ, 1916 Dec-1917 Apr (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Including to/from regarding Winchester proof reading religious books and articles, speaking engagements, to/from the Congregational Sunday School Publishing Society, 1917 Apr-June (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Including regarding professional book reviews, College Teaching at Hartford School of Religious Pedagogy, professional advice from Winchester, 1917 July-Nov (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Including regarding professional book reviews, College Teaching at Hartford School of Religious Pedagogy, professional advice from Winchester, job opportunity with World War I troops and recreation, 1917 Dec-1918 Jan-May (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Including professional referrals and regarding Winchester's Adult Discussion Course, "The Teaching Church", 1924-1927 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Including the Connecticut Congregational Council, the General Council of the Congregational Church, Job opportunities, regarding the publication articles by Winchester, 1928-1938 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Writings, Series II
  - Pamphlets and Speeches
    - "Making the Most of Life," "How to Train the Devotional Life," "Spiritual Values in Hymns," "Church, Home and Child", 1916, 1922, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Book-length works
    - "Curricula of Christian Education," including Table of Contents, Introduction, and chapters 1-2, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Curricula of Christian Education," including chapters 3-6, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "Curricula of Christian Education," including chapters 7-10, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "Curricula of Christian Education," including chapters 11-13 and hand-written notes, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "Curricula of Christian Education," including extrea/alternate chapters, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "The Teaching Church - A Discussion Course for Adults", 1925 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - "The Handbook of the Churches: A Survey of the Churches in Action", 1927 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Articles and essays
    - A - C, including "The Approaches to Religious Education," "Are the Sunday Schools Slipping or Picking Up?," "Culling the Hymnal", 1929, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - D - H, including "Do We Any Longer Need Christian Education?" and "Home School, and Playground", 1929, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - I - N, including "Lessons and Life" and "The Movies and World Brotherhood", 1916, 1917, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - P - S, including "Patriotism For Children," "Religion In the Home World," "The Religious Education of Adults," "Religious Education and the Liquor Problem" and "Shall We Have Religious Instruction In The Public Schools", 1921, 1926, 1927, 1928, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - T - W, including "Teaching Religion Today," "Where the Sunday School Begins", and "Why Educate Adults", 1916, 1921, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - W - Z, including "The World of Moral Order," "The World of Self and Society," and "The World of Toil and Service", 1921 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Subject Files, Series III
  - Sex Education
    - Correspondence regarding committee reports and the accumulation of information from sex education experts and religious leaders (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence regarding committee reports and the accumulation of information from sex education experts and religious leaders (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence regarding committee reports and the accumulation of information from sex education experts and religious leaders (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Materials including pamphlets, questionnaires, Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America sub-committee reports and situations where parents teach children about sex (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Materials including sub-committee reports, blank surveys of women, and situations where parents teach children about sex (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Materials including questions asked by girls, proposed Sunday School courses (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Race Relations Education
    - Reports and Correspondence regarding members of the Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America's Council of Correlation's sub-committee on Race Relations, reports from the sub-committee, and the accumulation of information from race relation education experts and religious leaders, 1924-1927, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Situation Surveys from New York City youths for the Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America's Council of Correlation's sub-committee on Race Relations, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Situation Surveys from New York City and Brooklyn NY youths for the Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America's Council of Correlation's sub-committee on Race Relations, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Situation Surveys from New York City and New Haven, CT youths for the Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America's Council of Correlation's sub-committee on Race Relations, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Situation Surveys from New Haven, CT, Fairfield, CT, and Wellesley, MA youths for the Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America's Council of Correlation's sub-committee on Race Relations, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Situation Surveys from Hartford, CT, Galesburg, IL, Bangor, ME, Brookline, MA and Wellesley, MA youths for the Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America's Council of Correlation's sub-committee on Race Relations, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Situation Surveys from Oberlin, OH youths for the Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America's Council of Correlation's sub-committee on Race Relations, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Situation Surveys from Oberlin, OH youths for the Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America's Council of Correlation's sub-committee on Race Relations and meeting minutes from the African Welfare sub-committee, 1925, 1933, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Prohibition / Temperance
    - Correspondence regarding asking Senators and Congressmen to ban the manufacture of alcohol, temperance education, to members of the Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America's Council of Correlation's sub-committee on Temperance Education, 1917-1926 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence regarding curriculum for temperance and Prohibition education, to members of the Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America's Council of Correlation's sub-committee on Temperance Education, 1927-1930, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Situation Surveys from Oberlin, OH, Toledo, OH, Nebraska, North Carolina, Illinois, and New York City for the Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America's Council of Correlation's sub-committee on Temperance Education, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Situation Surveys from New York City for the Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America's Council of Correlation's sub-committee on Temperance Education, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Situation Surveys from New Haven, CT for the Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America's Council of Correlation's sub-committee on Temperance Education, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Situation Surveys from New Haven, CT and Wellesley, MA for the Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America's Council of Correlation's sub-committee on Temperance Education, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Situation Surveys from Wellesley, MA for the Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America's Council of Correlation's sub-committee on Temperance Education, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Situation Surveys from Wellesley, MA for the Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America's Council of Correlation's sub-committee on Temperance Education, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Materials pertaining to temperance education including curriculum, minute meetings and discussions from the Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America's Council of Correlation's sub-committee on Temperance Education (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Materials pertaining to temperance education including curriculum, minute meetings and discussions from the Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America's Council of Correlation's sub-committee on Temperance Education (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Materials pertaining to temperance education including minute meetings and discussions from the Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America's Council of Correlation's sub-committee on Temperance Education (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Brochures, pamphlets, and newsletters pertaining to temperance and Prohibition (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Pamphlets, including: "Then Came Prohibition" by Bert H. Davis; "Will Prohibition Stand" by Claris Edwin Silcox, 1919-1929 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Peace
    - Brochures, pamphlets, and newsletters, 1920s (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Federal Council of Churches of America's Council of Correlation's Committee on Education for Peace: meeting minutes and notes, 1926, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Federal Council of Churches of America's Council of Correlation's Committee on Education for Peace: meeting minutes and notes, 1926, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - National Committee on the Churches and World Peace: meeting minutes and notes, Peace Education Materials: publications, curriculum and newsletters, 1936-1938 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Peace Education: curriculum, 1920s (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Peace Education: list of publications and materials, 1926-1927 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Peace Pageant by G. Aldo Randegger: pageant story and correspondence for the promotion of world peace, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Peace Education: pamphlets, papers, and correspondence relating to the role of the church in World War I, report on churches and world peace promotion, and graded Sunday School Lessons, 1917-1918, 1927 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Peace Education: pamphlets and papers promoting world peace, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Peace Education: pamphlets and papers promoting world peace, 1927-1929, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Peace Education: reports and curriculum for the promotion of world peace, 1925, 1926, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Peace Education: correspondence, 1915-1917, 1924, 1927 Mar (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Peace Education: correspondence, 1927 April-1928 Feb, 1929, 1935-1936 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Religious education
    - Adult Religious Education: Correspondence, committee notes, and curriculum from the International Council of Religious Education, 1928-1929 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Adult Religious Education: Committee notes and curriculum from the International Council of Religious Education, 1929-1930 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Adult Religious Education: Committee notes and curriculum from the International Council of Religious Education, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Adult Religious Education: Curriculum from the International Council of Religious Education, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Adult Religious Education: Curriculum from the International Council of Religious Education, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Adult Religious Education: Committee notes and curriculum from the International Council of Religious Education, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Adult Religious Education: Commitee notes and curriculum from the International Council of Religious Education, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Children' Fellowship of Prayer booklets, 1936-1938 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Church Schools: curriculum and reports on their establishment for the Internationl Council of Religious Education, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Congregational Sunday School Publishing Society Education Department and the Connecticut Council of Churches and Religious Education: budget information, notes concerning meetings on adult religious education, the Christian home, and other religious matters, 1915-1916, 1933, 1935-1937 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Connecticut Council of Churches and Religious Education: correspondence and Occasional Information Bulletins, 1935-1937 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Curriculum: papers and committee notes on religious education from the Federal Council of Churches of America's Council of Correlation of Programs for Religious Education, 1922 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Curriculum: lesson plans for religious education of children and adults, correspondence relating to Junior Sunday School Lessons Group Graded Lessons notes for the International Sunday School Council, 1916, 1927 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Curriculum: notes, correpsondence, and leaflets for the International Sunday School Committee's Sunday School Group Graded Lessons, 1924, 1926, 1928, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Curriculum: Sunday School Group Graded Lessons for the International Sunday School Committee, 1925, 1927, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Curriculum: Sunday School Group Graded Lessons for the International Sunday School Committee, including the American Indian series, 1922, 1923, 1926 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Curriculum: materials, reports, and articles on the Sunday School Lessons for the International Lesson Committee, 1913-1915 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Curriculum: materials and leaflets of the Sunday School Group Graded Lessons for the International Sunday School Committee, 1924, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Curriculum: reports and meeting minutes of the International Sunday School Committee for Sunday School Group Graded Lessons, 1920, 1922, 1923 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Curriculum: notes on Sunday School Group Graded Lessons for the International Sunday School Committee, 1917, 1924, 1927, 1929, 1930, 1939 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Curriculum: reports and minutes of the International Sunday School Lessons Committee meeting, 1924-1925 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Curriculum: minutes of the International Sunday School Lessons Committee meeting, 1926-1929 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Curriculum: correspondence relating to the International Sunday School Lessons Committee, 1913-1917 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Curriculum: correspondence relating to the International Sunday School Lessons Committee, 1918-19, 1921-1922, 1927, 1929, 1933-1935 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Curriculum: Typical and Life Situations to instruct young people in proper morals for the Federal Council of Churches of America's Council of Correlation of Programs for Religious Education (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Curriculum: Typical and Life Situations to instruct young people in proper morals for the Federal Council of Churches of America's Council of Correlation of Programs for Religious Education (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Curriculum: Typical and Life Situations to instruct young people in proper morals for the Federal Council of Churches of America's Council of Correlation of Programs for Religious Education (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Curriculum: Typical and Life Situations to instruct young people in proper morals for the Federal Council of Churches of America's Council of Correlation of Programs for Religious Education (Box 8, Folder 5)